<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Tech.Semicolon]]></title>
    <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/tags/collections.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-31T10:43:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel make custom class using console command]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/11/laravel-make-custom-class-using-console-command/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/11/laravel-make-custom-class-using-console-command/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel ships with built in console <code>make</code> commands to generate class files for controllers, models, migrations etc. For example creating a resourse controller, you can do :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:controller CustomerController --resource
</code></pre>

<p>Depending in your project structure and design patterns, you might be using different classes like repositories, services etc. We can take advantage of console commands to save time and create it just like we created controller above.</p>

<h3 id="file-generation-%3A">File generation :</h3>

<p>We firstly create a template file which is like a blueprint of how thw new class file will look like. This file is called <code>stub</code> file.</p>

<p>Then when command is run, we simply copy the stub to <code>class.php</code> and replace the dummyclass, dummynamespace etc with the new files class and namespace.</p>

<p>Above steps are made much simpler by <code>GeneratorCommand</code> class.</p>

<h3 id="the-generatorcommand-class-%3A">The GeneratorCommand class :</h3>

<p>Laravel's make commands extend an abstract class <code>GeneratorCommand</code>. This class basically has all the methods which do making a directory, getting content of stub, replacing class &amp; namespace, saving the new file and so on.</p>

<p>This is an abstract class which then extends the Illuminate <code>command</code> class.</p>

<h3 id="example-%3A">Example :</h3>

<p>Let's create a make command for generating <code>Repository</code> for a model.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create the stub :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a directory called <code>stubs</code> in laravel project root. I really like non-php files outside the app folder, you can put the stubs in the location you prefer.</p>

<p>Create a new file inside <code>stubs</code> directory called <code>Repository.stub</code>. We are eliminating the repository specific functions as the goal is to focus on creating class file. You can add your repository functions inside the stub or maybe create a base class and extend stubs class from it.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace DummyNamespace;

use App\DummyModel;

class DummyRepository
{
    protected $model;
    /**
       * Instantiate reporitory
       * 
       * @param DummyModel $model
       */
    public function __construct(DummyModel $model)
    {
        $this-&gt;model = $model;
    }

    // Your methods for repository
}
</code></pre>

<p>The usual idea is whatever is to be replaced, we prefix it with <code>Dummy</code>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating command :</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's create command scaffolding from artisan :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:command RepositoryMakeCommand
</code></pre>

<p>The make command classes are generally named in format <code>WhatToCreateMakeCommand</code>. If we had to create a service class, we could say <code>ServiceMakeCommand</code>.</p>

<p>We need to edit the <code>RepositoryMakeCommand.php</code> file which will be generated inside <code>app/Console/Commands</code> folder.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Console\Commands;

use Illuminate\Console\GeneratorCommand;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Input\InputArgument;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Exception\InvalidArgumentException;

class RepositoryMakeCommand extends GeneratorCommand
{
    /**
     * The name and signature of the console command.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $name = 'make:repository';

    /**
     * The console command description.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $description = 'Create a new model repository';

    /**
     * The type of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $type = 'Repository';

    /**
     * The name of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    private $repositoryClass;

    /**
     * The name of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    private $model;

    /**
     * Execute the console command.
     *
     * @return bool|null
     */
    public function fire(){

        $this-&gt;setRepositoryClass();

        $path = $this-&gt;getPath($this-&gt;repositoryClass);

        if ($this-&gt;alreadyExists($this-&gt;getNameInput())) {
            $this-&gt;error($this-&gt;type.' already exists!');

            return false;
        }

        $this-&gt;makeDirectory($path);

        $this-&gt;files-&gt;put($path, $this-&gt;buildClass($this-&gt;repositoryClass));

        $this-&gt;info($this-&gt;type.' created successfully.');

        $this-&gt;line("&lt;info&gt;Created Repository :&lt;/info&gt; $this-&gt;repositoryClass");
    }

    /**
     * Set repository class name
     *
     * @return  void
     */
    private function setRepositoryClass()
    {
        $name = ucwords(strtolower($this-&gt;argument('name')));

        $this-&gt;model = $name;

        $modelClass = $this-&gt;parseName($name);

        $this-&gt;repositoryClass = $modelClass . 'Repository';

        return $this;
    }

    /**
     * Replace the class name for the given stub.
     *
     * @param  string  $stub
     * @param  string  $name
     * @return string
     */
    protected function replaceClass($stub, $name)
    {
        if(!$this-&gt;argument('name')){
            throw new InvalidArgumentException("Missing required argument model name");
        }

        $stub = parent::replaceClass($stub, $name);

        return str_replace('DummyModel', $this-&gt;model, $stub);
    }

    /**
     * 
     * Get the stub file for the generator.
     *
     * @return string
     */
    protected function getStub()
    {
        return  base_path('stubs/Repository.stub');
    }
    /**
     * Get the default namespace for the class.
     *
     * @param  string  $rootNamespace
     * @return string
     */
    protected function getDefaultNamespace($rootNamespace)
    {
        return $rootNamespace . '\Repo';
    }

    /**
     * Get the console command arguments.
     *
     * @return array
     */
    protected function getArguments()
    {
        return [
            ['name', InputArgument::REQUIRED, 'The name of the model class.'],
        ];
    }
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Registering the command :</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally we need to register this command to make available in artisan console. We can do that by adding it inside <code>app/Console/Kernel.php</code>.</p>

<p>Inside <code>protected $commands = []</code> array add the class path :</p>

<pre><code class="php">\App\Console\Commands\RepositoryMakeCommand::class,
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Using the command :</li>
</ul>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:repository Customer
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a <code>CustomerRepository.php</code> inside <code>app/Repo</code> folder :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Repo;

use App\Customer;

class CustomerRepository
{
    protected $model;
    /**
       * Instantiate reporitory
       * 
       * @param Customer $model
       */
    public function __construct(Customer $model)
    {
        $this-&gt;model = $model;
    }

    // Your methods for repository
}
</code></pre>

<p>You can extend this implementation as per your project structure needs. This indeed saves time in longer run and makes sure all generated classes have common blueprint structure.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel tap vs tap vs pipe]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/08/laravel-tap-vs-tap-vs-pipe/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/08/laravel-tap-vs-tap-vs-pipe/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are wondering having tap 2 times in the article title is a mistake, apparently it is not. Laravel has large set of helper functions which are generic and helper functions specific to collections. Tap and pipe are very popular amongst laravel enthusiasts. Let's dive into each of of those to see what really makes them special and what differentiates them :</p>

<h3 id="the-tap-function-%3A">The tap() function :</h3>

<p>The reason of having tap 2 times in the article header is that, there are 2 implementations of tap helper function in laravel. One is in generic context and one specific to handling collections.</p>

<ul>
<li>The generic tap() function :</li>
</ul>

<p>The name tap suggests that it basically does set of actions using the value and then returns the value as if nothing happened. In other words, the tap function accepts two arguments <code>$value</code> and <code>a Closure</code>. The <code>$value</code> will be passed to the closure function. You can perform your actions in the closure where the return value of the Closure is irrelevant. At the end tap returns the same <code>$value</code> at the end.</p>

<p>For example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user, function ($user) {

    $user-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail());

});
</code></pre>

<p>In the above snippet, we are passing <code>$user</code> instance to tap as first argument which is then cascaded as a parameter to closure. The closure will execute and basically send a new welcome email. Then control will come back to tap which will return the <code>$user</code> instance back.</p>

<p>Even you can just eliminate the closure and call function on it directly like below.</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user)-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail());
</code></pre>

<p>The above will still return the user instance. The beauty of it is, you can chain the tap calls. Let's say you need to update the user role, then send the welcome email and then assign user some permissions. You can chain it all like :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user)-&gt;update([
    'role' =&gt; 'Customer' 
])
-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail())
-&gt;assignPermissions('CustomerRole');
</code></pre>

<p>The use of this method can be handy when certain methods do not return the object as you want. A great example is the update method itself on the eloquent model. It returns integer when used otherwise. But if used as above with tap function, it returns the object it performed the update.</p>

<ul>
<li>The collection tap() function :</li>
</ul>

<p>The tap function for collection can be used in collection function chaining. I think of it similar to javascript debug breakpoints. You pin it to print something at a point of time in your javascript and then move ahead after removing the breakpoint.</p>

<p>For example consider following example :</p>

<pre><code class="php"><br />$customers = collect([
    ['name' =&gt; 'mihir',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'george', 'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'silver'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'nathen', 'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'platinum'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'steve',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'shawn',  'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'gold']
]);

$activeGoldCustomers = collect($customers)
    -&gt;where('is_active', true)
    -&gt;tap(function ($activeCustomers) {
        $this-&gt;sendActiveCustomerEmail($activeCustomers);
    })
    -&gt;where('category', 'gold')
    -&gt;tap(function ($goldCustomers) {
        $this-&gt;sendOfferCode('100%Discount');
    });
</code></pre>

<p>In above example, we are just returning the customers who are currently active and fall under category gold. However, using the tap function we can perform certain actions on the go as we filter those. When we filtered for <code>is_active = true</code>, we sent activation email. Then when we added another filter for <code>category = gold</code>, we sent offer code just for active customer from gold category.</p>

<p>You can also find this handy in dumping data for debugging during the developement cycle.</p>

<p>The fundamental concept of <code>tap()</code> is just use the value and perform actions but NEVER CHANGE the value. If you think then what can change the value? <code>pipe()</code> is the answer.</p>

<h3 id="the-pipe-function-%3A">The pipe() function :</h3>

<p>Pipe function is just applicable for collections. For example consider following example :</p>

<pre><code class="php"><br />$customers = collect([
    ['name' =&gt; 'mihir',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'george', 'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'silver'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'nathen', 'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'platinum'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'steve',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'shawn',  'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'gold']
]);

$counts = collect($customers)
 -&gt;pipe(function($customers) {
    return [
        'active_count'      =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('is_active', true)-&gt;count(),
        'gold_count'        =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'gold')-&gt;count(),
        'silver_count'      =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'silver')-&gt;count(),
        'platinum_count'    =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'platinum')-&gt;count()
    ];
});
</code></pre>

<p>Above will basicaly return <code>[3, 3, 1, 1]</code>, but it is very clean and less code is always better.</p>

<p>Please note that the <code>pipe()</code> helper method is different than the <code>laravel pipelines</code>. However, if you read about pipelines, its is kind of similar conceptually to generic tap function where you can pass an object through multiple classes to perform set of task and then return the result value once all the tasks have been finished. A <a href="https://medium.com/@jeffochoa/understanding-laravel-pipelines-a7191f75c351">handy article</a> for the same is <a href="https://medium.com/@jeffochoa/understanding-laravel-pipelines-a7191f75c351">here</a> if you want a quick read.</p>

<p>Even if these methods are very handy, sometimes if you chain it to much it loses the element fo readability. I will suggest it is preferable to follow what the domain logic wants and group the similar processes together to tap or pipe.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>