<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Tech.Semicolon]]></title>
    <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/tags/php.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-27T13:33:09+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel use secure SSL connection while using AWS RDS]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/04/10/laravel-rds-ssl-encryption-in-transit/"/>
            <updated>2019-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/04/10/laravel-rds-ssl-encryption-in-transit/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Amazon Relational Database Service Amazon RDS is a cloud based web service that makes things easier to set up, operate, and scale a relational databases on the cloud. It has become one of the popular choices when setting up laravel database infrastructure.</p>

<ul>
<li>Quick question :</li>
</ul>

<p>If you are using AWS RDS in your laravel application, is your connection encrypted in transit? Or so ask other way around, is your laravel application connecting to AWS RDS using a secure SSL connection?</p>

<p>If you think that RDS comes up with secure encryption in transit, you are right, it implements SSL. However, is it turned on somehow by default or is it there when we use it directly? Not really.. I had a perception that my laravel app is secured in transit by SSL encryption until I found out its not.</p>

<ul>
<li>Let's find out :</li>
</ul>

<p>Connect to the environment/server/container where laravel is hosted and run tinker :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan tinker
</code></pre>

<p>Once, the tinker prompt is open, run following :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">&gt;&gt;&gt; DB::select("SHOW STATUS LIKE 'Ssl_cipher'")
</code></pre>

<p>If it gives output like following :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">=&gt; [
    {
        +"Variable_name": "Ssl_cipher",
        +"Value": "DHE-RSA-AES128-SHA",
    },
]
</code></pre>

<p>Then laravel application is connecting to AWS RDS via a secure SSL connection.</p>

<p>However, if the output is like this  :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">=&gt; [
    {
        +"Variable_name": "Ssl_cipher",
        +"Value": "",
    },
]
</code></pre>

<p>Then the connection is not sure. There are number of variables which you can help us get more information about the SSL connection paramaters. We checked <code>Ssl_cipher</code> above, you can also check <code>Ssl_version</code> which might give you blank or something like <code>TLSv1</code> if SSL is working.</p>

<p>To get all information about SSL connection run following in tinker prompt :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">&gt;&gt;&gt; DB::select("SHOW STATUS LIKE '%Ssl%'")
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Next steps to secure the connection :</li>
</ul>

<p>If you found out that the laravel application connection is not using SSL while connecting to AWS RDS, you can follow below steps to enable the same.</p>

<p>Firstly, let us understand how it works. When you connect to AWS RDS normally via mysql cli, you do :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">mysql -h myinstance.c9akciq32.rds-us-east-1.amazonaws.com -u username -p
</code></pre>

<p>You can pass SSL certificate using <code>--ssl-ca</code> option in above command like below :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">mysql -h myinstance.c9akciq32.rds-us-east-1.amazonaws.com --ssl-ca=/path/to/certificate-authority-file.pem -u username -p
</code></pre>

<p>Optionally, you can pass <code>-ssl-mode</code> and <code>--ssl-verify-server-cert</code>. For more details about this please refer mysql's official <a href="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/encrypted-connection-options.html">documentation</a>.</p>

<p>Now let's get back to the original problem which we are here to solve. How we are going to do this in Laravel?</p>

<p>Step 1 : Downloading the <code>certificate authority file</code>. AWS RDS has a commonly published pem file called <code>rds-combined-ca-bundle.pem</code> which you can download directly from <a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/rds-downloads/rds-combined-ca-bundle.pem">here</a>. It is an officially published pem file which will work in all default RDS SSL connections.</p>

<p>Step 2 : Save the downloaded file from step 1 inside a new directory called <code>RDSCerts</code> inside laravel root. Quick note that in this step itself, I would add this inside gitignore because there is no need to add pem and cert files inside the version control.</p>

<p>Step 3 : Laravel's database configurations are inside <code>config/database.php</code> file. It already has a <code>mysql</code> section. Let's not change that, lets copy that entirely into a new configuration section called <code>mysql_ssl</code> where we will also add the certification authority file in options like below :</p>

<pre><code class="php">'mysql_ssl' =&gt; [
    'driver' =&gt; 'mysql',
    'host' =&gt; env('DB_HOST', '127.0.0.1'),
    'port' =&gt; env('DB_PORT', '3306'),
    'database' =&gt; env('DB_DATABASE', 'forge'),
    'username' =&gt; env('DB_USERNAME', 'forge'),
    'password' =&gt; env('DB_PASSWORD', ''),
    'unix_socket' =&gt; env('DB_SOCKET', ''),
    'charset' =&gt; 'utf8mb4',
    'collation' =&gt; 'utf8mb4_unicode_ci',
    'prefix' =&gt; '',
    'prefix_indexes' =&gt; true,
    'strict' =&gt; false,
    'engine' =&gt; null,
    'options' =&gt; [    
        PDO::MYSQL_ATTR_SSL_CA =&gt; base_path('RDSCerts/rds-combined-ca-bundle.pem')
    ],
],
</code></pre>

<p>Important note, You might be thinking that when we need to pass <code>--ssl-verify-server-cert</code> option somehow from laravel's configuration as well. Don't worry it's enabled by default. If you want to disable it then you can pass <code>PDO::MYSQL_ATTR_SSL_VERIFY_SERVER_CERT = false</code> which I would not suggest.</p>

<p>There are more options about SSL which you can check in the official PDO <a href="https://www.php.net/manual/en/ref.pdo-mysql.php">documentation</a>.</p>

<p>Once you follow above 3 steps, you should be good to go. Cross check by running <code>DB::select("SHOW STATUS LIKE '%Ssl%'")</code> in tinker as we did earlier in this article. You should see ciphers and ssl version mentioned in the connection.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel finally has higher level orWhere for query scopes]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/03/17/laravel-finally-has-higher-level-or-where/"/>
            <updated>2019-03-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/03/17/laravel-finally-has-higher-level-or-where/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel's excellent querybuilder and Eloquent ORM is handy as ever. But with newer version of laravel, it's much more simpler. 5.8 is here already and this feature has not been talked as much because it seems a minor feature release. Let's dive in with an example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App;

use Illuminate\Foundation\Auth\User as Authenticatable;
use Role;

class User extends Authenticatable
{
    /**
     * The attributes that should be hidden for arrays.
     *
     * @var array
     */
    protected $hidden = [

        'password', 'remember_token',
    ];

    /*
     * The attributes that should be mutated to dates.
     *
     * @var array
     */
    protected $dates = ['deleted_at'];

    /**
     * Scope a query to only filter admin users.
     *
     * @param \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder $query
     * @return \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder
     */
    public function scopeAdmin($query)
    {
        return $query-&gt;where('role', Role::Admin);
    }

    /**
     * Scope a query to only filter reviewer users.
     *
     * @param \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder $query
     * @return \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder
     */
    public function scopeReviewer($query)
    {
        return $query-&gt;where('role', Role::Reviewer);
    }

    /**
     * Scope a query to only filter customer users.
     *
     * @param \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder $query
     * @return \Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder
     */
    public function scopeCustomer($query)
    {
        return $query-&gt;where('role', Role::Customer);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The use case is, we want to get the users who are either has <code>admin</code> or <code>reviewer</code> role.</p>

<p>For earlier versions of laravel(version &lt; 5.8), we would do :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$users = App\User::admin()-&gt;orWhere(function (Builder $query) {
    $query-&gt;reviewer();
})-&gt;get();
</code></pre>

<p>There is nothing difficult in above eloquent query but having a closure just to filter a scope for an orWhere clause seems too much sometimes. But that case is no more valid after 5.8 releases. Now we can do :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$users = App\User::admin()-&gt;orWhere-&gt;reviewer()-&gt;get();
</code></pre>

<p>And that's it. It's a very small change but makes the code much more simpler to implement and read. Sometimes you might get lost in the closures when the query is large. Features like this makes it much more comfortable to implement.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel has one through]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/03/13/laravel-has-one-through/"/>
            <updated>2019-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/03/13/laravel-has-one-through/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel 5.8 is now released and one thing from the release notes many people might be waiting for is the <code>hasOneThrough</code> relationship. Laravel ealier had <code>hasManyThrough</code>, but with the addition of <code>hasOneThrough</code> it's more flexible. Let's dive into an example :</p>

<p>Consider we have <code>User</code> Model, <code>Reviewer</code> Model and <code>Activity</code> Model with structure :</p>

<pre><code>users
    id - integer
    reviewer_id - integer

reviewers
    id - integer

activities
    id - integer
    user_id - integer
</code></pre>

<p>Each <code>reviewer</code> has one <code>user</code>, and each <code>user</code> is associated with one user <code>activity</code> record. If we want to get <code>activity</code> from <code>reviewer</code>, there is no <code>reviewer_id</code> column in <code>activities</code> table, in such case we can use <code>hasOneThrough</code> relation. Let's define the relationship now :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App;

use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;

class Reviewer extends Model
{
    /**
     * Get the reviewer's activity.
     */
    public function activity()
    {
        return $this-&gt;hasOneThrough('App\Activity', 'App\User');
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>To understand more, lets use Laravel conventional terms on the models. In this case the <code>Activity</code> is the final model we would need to relate, while <code>User</code> is the intermediate model.</p>

<p>As all other relationships in Laravel, we can also explicitely specify the foreign keys while definining <code>hasOneThrough</code> relation, Let's do that for this example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App;

use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;

class Reviewer extends Model
{
    /**
     * Get the reviewer's activity.
     */
    public function activity()
    {
        return $this-&gt;hasOneThrough(
            'App\Activity',
            'App\User',
            'reviewer_id', // Foreign key on users table...
            'user_id', // Foreign key on activities table...
            'id', // Local key on reviewers table...
            'id' // Local key on users table...
        );
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now you can easily do :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$reviewer = Reviewer::first();
$activity = $reviewer-&gt;activity;
</code></pre>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel liming chunk collection]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/02/12/laravel-limiting-chunk-collection/"/>
            <updated>2019-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/02/12/laravel-limiting-chunk-collection/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>Little Intro about <code>chunk</code> :</li>
</ul>

<p>Laravel comes up with an excellent Eloquent ORM. There are lot of cool things in Eloquent, one of which is <code>chunk</code> method.</p>

<p>Usually when you need to process large data, lets say you want to update <code>users</code> table and assign a coupon code based on 3rd party APIs.</p>

<p>What you can do is :</p>

<pre><code class="php">User::get()-&gt;each(function($user){

    $coupon = API::getCouponCode($user-&gt;email);
    $user-&gt;coupon = $coupon;
    $user-&gt;save();
});
</code></pre>

<p>Doing this is good but if you have thousands of users, loading them all up at once to do the coupon saving process. That's going to take consume a hige memory at a time and maybe the server will be exusted because so much data is stored in memory for processing at a time.</p>

<p>The <code>chunk</code> method helps these kind of implementations. Chunking records means taking a batch of records by a limit, process those, take the next batch processing those and so on... The idea is you are taking a subset of data to process at a time instead of entire data loaded into memory.</p>

<p>The chunk method will retrieve a "chunk" of Eloquent models, feeding them to a given Closure for processing. Using the chunk method will conserve memory when working with large result sets.</p>

<p>Lets do the same but with chunk this time :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$recodsPerBatch = 50;

User::chunk($recodsPerBatch, function($user){

    $coupon = API::getCouponCode($user-&gt;email);
    $user-&gt;coupon = $coupon;
    $user-&gt;save();
});
</code></pre>

<p>Now, as you can probably guess this will take 50 user records at a time to process, once  those are completed it will take next 50 untill all records are procesed by chunk closure.</p>

<ul>
<li>The main problem <code>Limit</code> with <code>Chunk</code> :</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's apply limit to the above example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$recodsPerBatch = 50;

User::limit(100)-&gt;chunk($recodsPerBatch, function($user){

    $coupon = API::getCouponCode($user-&gt;email);
    $user-&gt;coupon = $coupon;
    $user-&gt;save();
});
</code></pre>

<p>If you would think laravel will chunk 50 records in 2 batches are we are limiting the total records to 100, oops not really.</p>

<p>Laravel will do series of queries like below to chunk the records :</p>

<pre><code class="sql">select * from `users` limit 50 offset 0
select * from `users` limit 50 offset 50
select * from `users` limit 50 offset 100
...
</code></pre>

<p>The chunk method <code>ignores</code> any previous eloquent method which applies limit. It can be <code>limit</code> and <code>offset</code> OR <code>take</code> and <code>skip</code>...</p>

<p>This becomes a problem for which lot of people had raised an issue on laravel's github repo. But Laravel's core dev team mentioned this is the expected behaviour and rightfully so.. Chunk itself is using limit to convert entire collection in batches.</p>

<ul>
<li>And.... Here it is.. The Solution you were waiting for :</li>
</ul>

<p>Laravel has a chunk variation called <code>chunkById</code>. Let's use the first example and implement <code>chunkById</code> now :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$recodsPerBatch = 50;

User::chunkById($recodsPerBatch, function($user){

    $coupon = API::getCouponCode($user-&gt;email);
    $user-&gt;coupon = $coupon;
    $user-&gt;save();
});
</code></pre>

<p>The main and only fundamental difference between <code>chunk</code> and <code>chunkById</code> is how it structures the query.</p>

<pre><code class="sql">select * from `users` where `id` &gt; 0 order by `id` asc limit 50
select * from `users` where `id` &gt; 0 and `id` &gt; 50 order by `id` asc limit 50
select * from `users` where `id` &gt; 0 and `id` &gt; 50 and `id` &gt; 100 order by `id` asc limit 50
select * from `users` where `id` &gt; 0 and `id` &gt; 50 and `id` &gt; 100 and `id` &gt; 150 order by `id` asc limit 50
...
</code></pre>

<p>If you observer in the queries done by <code>chunkById</code> :</p>

<ol>
<li>It's adding an order by clause to the id column (By the way you can specify the column as 3rd argument to chunkById method if itis not id)</li>
<li>It adds <code>where id &gt; x</code> each time it processes the next batch</li>
<li>There is no <code>offset</code> used and <code>id</code> column is used conceptually as an offset.</li>
</ol>

<p>This gives you an advantage that you can add your offset in the query using <code>id</code> column as a limit just like <code>chunkById</code> is doing internallu.</p>

<p>Let's limit the chunk in our example with 100 records to chunk :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$recodsPerBatch = 50;

$limit = 100;

$maxId = User::orderBy('id', 'asc')-&gt;offset($limit)-&gt;limit(1)-&gt;select('id')-&gt;first()-&gt;id;

User::where('id', '&lt;', $maxId)-&gt;chunkById($recodsPerBatch, function($user){

    $coupon = API::getCouponCode($user-&gt;email);
    $user-&gt;coupon = $coupon;
    $user-&gt;save();
});
</code></pre>

<p>What we did was, even if we can not use limit directly, we got an id which falls just above the limit we want. Used that to add a where clause of <code>where('id', '&lt;', $maxId)</code>.</p>

<p>This will then chunk the 100 results, with 2 batches of 50 records in each batch. Cool, isn't it!</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP argument validation using assert]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/12/php-argument-validation-using-assert/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/12/php-argument-validation-using-assert/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When creating classes, we either pass arguments to the constructor function or have setter-getter functions to access class properties. These arguments may sometime have a specific format or requirements. For Example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">/**
 * $age integer
 *
 * @return  string
 */
function($age){
    return "You are $age years old";
}
</code></pre>

<p>Above function expects $age to be an integer. If any other type is passed, function will no work as expected.</p>

<p>The example was very granular. When your core classes have functions which affect important domain logics of your project, argument validation becomes an  important part.</p>

<p>PHP comes with default function(or more specifically a language construct for PHP version 7) called <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/function.assert.php"><code>assert</code></a>, which basically checks if provided assertion if false. If yes then you can handle the exceptions in callback. Even if this is useful, I will strongly suggest using composer plugin <a href="https://github.com/webmozart/assert">webmozart/assert</a> for this. It has very useful intuitive methods for the same.</p>

<ul>
<li>Example :</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's consider a function <code>placeOrder()</code> which takes array of <code>$items</code> having instances of <code>Item</code> class, a <code>$shippingPrice</code> and <code>$customer</code> having instance of <code>Customer</code> class.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php 

use Webmozart\Assert\Assert;

Class Order{

    /**
     * Array of Item instances
     * @var array
     */
    private $items;

    /**
     * Shipping Price
     * @var float
     */
    private $shippingPrice;

    /**
     * Customer Instance
     * @var Customer
     */
    private $customer;

    /**
     * Instantiate Order class
     * 
     * @param $items
     * @param $shippingPrice
     * @param $customer
     */
    function __construct($items, $shippingPrice, $customer)
    {
        Assert::isArray($items, '$items must be an array. Got: %s');
        Assert::allIsInstanceOf($items, '\Item', '$items must contain array of Item class instances. Got: %s');
        Assert::numeric($shippingPrice, '$shippingPrice must be numeric. Got: %s');
        Assert::isInstanceOf($customer, '\Customer', '$customer must be an instance of Customer class. Got: %s');

        $this-&gt;shippingPrice    = $shippingPrice;
        $this-&gt;customer         = $customer;
        $this-&gt;items            = $items;
    }

    /**
     * Places order
     * 
     * @return Order
     */
    public function placeOrder(){

        // PlaceOrder
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, when we instantiate the order class :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$customer = new Customer('John Doe');

$order = new Order([], 12.22, $customer);
</code></pre>

<p>We are passing an invalid value for <code>$items</code> argument. It will throw <code>\InvalidArgumentException</code> with error message : <code>$items must contain array of Item class instances. Got: Array</code>.</p>

<p>If you are using setter-getter functions instead of constructor parameters, you can have these assertions inside the setter functions. Above methodology is sometimes referred as defensive programming where we are making sure function will not break at the intial stages itself. The counter concept of defensive programming will be validating these arguments as and when they are actually used inside <code>placeOrder</code> function.</p>

<p>Advantages :</p>

<ol>
<li>Prevents errors caused due to unexpected type of arguments passed</li>
<li>Easier to debug</li>
<li>Easier to create unit tests and catch asset exceptions</li>
<li>Easier to write readable custom error messages</li>
</ol>

<p>Disadvantages :</p>

<p>If not properly thought, duplicate validations can cause redundancies. For example in above case, if instance of <code>Item</code> class contains a valid price is a concern of <code>Item</code> class. If that validation is also present in <code>Order</code> class as well, it created redundancies.</p>

<p>You can find more assertion options available here : <a href="https://github.com/webmozart/assert">https://github.com/webmozart/assert</a></p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel make custom class using console command]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/11/laravel-make-custom-class-using-console-command/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/11/laravel-make-custom-class-using-console-command/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel ships with built in console <code>make</code> commands to generate class files for controllers, models, migrations etc. For example creating a resourse controller, you can do :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:controller CustomerController --resource
</code></pre>

<p>Depending in your project structure and design patterns, you might be using different classes like repositories, services etc. We can take advantage of console commands to save time and create it just like we created controller above.</p>

<h3 id="file-generation-%3A">File generation :</h3>

<p>We firstly create a template file which is like a blueprint of how thw new class file will look like. This file is called <code>stub</code> file.</p>

<p>Then when command is run, we simply copy the stub to <code>class.php</code> and replace the dummyclass, dummynamespace etc with the new files class and namespace.</p>

<p>Above steps are made much simpler by <code>GeneratorCommand</code> class.</p>

<h3 id="the-generatorcommand-class-%3A">The GeneratorCommand class :</h3>

<p>Laravel's make commands extend an abstract class <code>GeneratorCommand</code>. This class basically has all the methods which do making a directory, getting content of stub, replacing class &amp; namespace, saving the new file and so on.</p>

<p>This is an abstract class which then extends the Illuminate <code>command</code> class.</p>

<h3 id="example-%3A">Example :</h3>

<p>Let's create a make command for generating <code>Repository</code> for a model.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create the stub :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a directory called <code>stubs</code> in laravel project root. I really like non-php files outside the app folder, you can put the stubs in the location you prefer.</p>

<p>Create a new file inside <code>stubs</code> directory called <code>Repository.stub</code>. We are eliminating the repository specific functions as the goal is to focus on creating class file. You can add your repository functions inside the stub or maybe create a base class and extend stubs class from it.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace DummyNamespace;

use App\DummyModel;

class DummyRepository
{
    protected $model;
    /**
       * Instantiate reporitory
       * 
       * @param DummyModel $model
       */
    public function __construct(DummyModel $model)
    {
        $this-&gt;model = $model;
    }

    // Your methods for repository
}
</code></pre>

<p>The usual idea is whatever is to be replaced, we prefix it with <code>Dummy</code>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating command :</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's create command scaffolding from artisan :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:command RepositoryMakeCommand
</code></pre>

<p>The make command classes are generally named in format <code>WhatToCreateMakeCommand</code>. If we had to create a service class, we could say <code>ServiceMakeCommand</code>.</p>

<p>We need to edit the <code>RepositoryMakeCommand.php</code> file which will be generated inside <code>app/Console/Commands</code> folder.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Console\Commands;

use Illuminate\Console\GeneratorCommand;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Input\InputArgument;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Exception\InvalidArgumentException;

class RepositoryMakeCommand extends GeneratorCommand
{
    /**
     * The name and signature of the console command.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $name = 'make:repository';

    /**
     * The console command description.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $description = 'Create a new model repository';

    /**
     * The type of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $type = 'Repository';

    /**
     * The name of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    private $repositoryClass;

    /**
     * The name of class being generated.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    private $model;

    /**
     * Execute the console command.
     *
     * @return bool|null
     */
    public function fire(){

        $this-&gt;setRepositoryClass();

        $path = $this-&gt;getPath($this-&gt;repositoryClass);

        if ($this-&gt;alreadyExists($this-&gt;getNameInput())) {
            $this-&gt;error($this-&gt;type.' already exists!');

            return false;
        }

        $this-&gt;makeDirectory($path);

        $this-&gt;files-&gt;put($path, $this-&gt;buildClass($this-&gt;repositoryClass));

        $this-&gt;info($this-&gt;type.' created successfully.');

        $this-&gt;line("&lt;info&gt;Created Repository :&lt;/info&gt; $this-&gt;repositoryClass");
    }

    /**
     * Set repository class name
     *
     * @return  void
     */
    private function setRepositoryClass()
    {
        $name = ucwords(strtolower($this-&gt;argument('name')));

        $this-&gt;model = $name;

        $modelClass = $this-&gt;parseName($name);

        $this-&gt;repositoryClass = $modelClass . 'Repository';

        return $this;
    }

    /**
     * Replace the class name for the given stub.
     *
     * @param  string  $stub
     * @param  string  $name
     * @return string
     */
    protected function replaceClass($stub, $name)
    {
        if(!$this-&gt;argument('name')){
            throw new InvalidArgumentException("Missing required argument model name");
        }

        $stub = parent::replaceClass($stub, $name);

        return str_replace('DummyModel', $this-&gt;model, $stub);
    }

    /**
     * 
     * Get the stub file for the generator.
     *
     * @return string
     */
    protected function getStub()
    {
        return  base_path('stubs/Repository.stub');
    }
    /**
     * Get the default namespace for the class.
     *
     * @param  string  $rootNamespace
     * @return string
     */
    protected function getDefaultNamespace($rootNamespace)
    {
        return $rootNamespace . '\Repo';
    }

    /**
     * Get the console command arguments.
     *
     * @return array
     */
    protected function getArguments()
    {
        return [
            ['name', InputArgument::REQUIRED, 'The name of the model class.'],
        ];
    }
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Registering the command :</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally we need to register this command to make available in artisan console. We can do that by adding it inside <code>app/Console/Kernel.php</code>.</p>

<p>Inside <code>protected $commands = []</code> array add the class path :</p>

<pre><code class="php">\App\Console\Commands\RepositoryMakeCommand::class,
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Using the command :</li>
</ul>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:repository Customer
</code></pre>

<p>This will create a <code>CustomerRepository.php</code> inside <code>app/Repo</code> folder :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Repo;

use App\Customer;

class CustomerRepository
{
    protected $model;
    /**
       * Instantiate reporitory
       * 
       * @param Customer $model
       */
    public function __construct(Customer $model)
    {
        $this-&gt;model = $model;
    }

    // Your methods for repository
}
</code></pre>

<p>You can extend this implementation as per your project structure needs. This indeed saves time in longer run and makes sure all generated classes have common blueprint structure.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel improving readability with blade directives]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/10/laravel-improving-readility-with-blade-directives/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/10/laravel-improving-readility-with-blade-directives/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel's blade templating system comes with ability to define custom directives. These directives can be very handly to improve readability of the view files. Let's do a quick recap of directives :</p>

<h3 id="blade-directives-%3A">Blade directives :</h3>

<ul>
<li>Generic directive :</li>
</ul>

<p>These directive take an argument and simply return the actions done in callback.</p>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::directive('caps', function ($expression) {
    return "&lt;?php echo ucwords($expression); ?&gt;";
});
</code></pre>

<p>You can use above in blade templates directly :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;div&gt;{{ @cap('john smith') }}&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<p>It is little tricky to handle the <code>$expresssion</code> in the callback, as if you pass an array or multiple string arguments, those are passed as single string expressions. You can see that shortly in action in usage ideas section.</p>

<ul>
<li>Conditional directive :</li>
</ul>

<p>These directives take an argument and use it inside callback to return value. Now the callback's return value is then casted as boolean to consider if statements inside it will be showed or now. It is just like <code>@if ... @endif</code> directive, but more intuitive.</p>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::if('isadmin', function ($user) {
    return $user-&gt;role == 'admin';
});
</code></pre>

<p>You can use above in blade templates directly :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@isadmin($user)
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;a href="{{ route('users.all') }}"&gt;See all users&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
@endisadmin
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<p>Above is similar to this if done in usual without the conditional directive :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@if($user-&gt;role == 'admin')
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;a href="{{ route('users.all') }}"&gt;See all users&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
@endif
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<h3 id="some-usage-ideas-%3A">Some usage ideas :</h3>

<p>These directive give a great advantage to simplify your blade views and make them more readable. See few examples below :</p>

<ol>
<li>Conditional role checks :</li>
</ol>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::if('role', function ($role) {

    // Not logged in
    if(!auth()-&gt;check()){
        return false;
    }

    // Multiple roles passed in argument
    if(is_array($role)){
        return in_array(auth()-&gt;user()-&gt;role, $role);
    }

    // Single role passed in argument
    return auth()-&gt;user()-&gt;role == $role;
});
</code></pre>

<p>This makes the role conditional checks in blade much easier :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@role('admin')
   &lt;!-- something only an admin can see--&gt;
@elserole(['customer', 'seller'])
   &lt;!-- something only a customer or a seller an see--&gt;
@endrole
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<ol start="2">
<li>Rendering form errors :</li>
</ol>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::directive('validation', function ($expression) {

    // $expression is a string expression and 
    // hence will be a string maintaing start and end quotes
    // Trimming the quotes
    $expression = str_replace(['(', ')'], '', $expression);
    $fieldName  = trim(trim($expression, '"'), '\'');

    $errors = \Session::get('errors', new \Illuminate\Support\MessageBag);

    if($errors-&gt;has($fieldName)){
        return '&lt;span role="alert"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;' . $errors-&gt;first($fieldName) . '&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;';
    }

    return;
});
</code></pre>

<p>This makes the the validation errors from server end much easier in forms :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code>&lt;form role="form" method="POST" action="{{ route('some.url') }}"&gt;
    @csrf
    &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;First Name *&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input class="form-control" placeholder="Enter your first name" name="first_name"&gt;
        @validation("first_name")
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Last Name *&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input class="form-control" placeholder="Enter your last name" name="last_name"&gt;
        @validation("last_name")
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;button type="submit" class="btn btn-primary"&gt;Submit Ticket&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<ol start="3">
<li>Dumping values in views fo debugging :</li>
</ol>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::directive('dd', function ($expression) {

    // $expression is a string expression and 
    // It can not be directly passed in dd($expression)
    // We can use with() helper which basically encapsulate the syntax
    // to render it properly in blade files
    return "&lt;?php dd(with({$expression})); ?&gt;";
});
</code></pre>

<p>Please note that above will not work for multiple arguments, can dd one argumenet only. Above can be then used :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@dd([1,2,3,4]);
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<ol start="4">
<li>Assigning values to variables in a view :</li>
</ol>

<p>Now this might be a very less possible requirement but if you want to assign a variable in a view, generally you do something like :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@php 
    $name = "John Doe";
@endphp
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<p>However, we can do this using blade directive :</p>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::directive('assign', function ($expression) {

    // The $expression passed in closure is a string in format '($name), value'
    // Hence we first remove the paranthesis and explode by comma
    list($name, $value) = explode(', ', str_replace(['(', ')'], '', $expression));
    return "&lt;?php {$name} = {$value}; ?&gt;";
});
</code></pre>

<p>And then simply use it as (Below example is very very simple but you can use as per your preference) :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">@assign($name, 'John Doe')

&lt;div&gt; {{ $name }} &lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<ol start="5">
<li>Frequent HTML elements :</li>
</ol>

<p>If you are using 3rd party HTML libraries like glyphicon or font-awesome, you need to use those in lot of places. You can use blade directive like :</p>

<pre><code class="php">Blade::directive('icon', function ($expression) {

    // The $expression passed in closure is a string in format '($name), value'
    // Hence we first remove the paranthesis and explode by comma
    $classes = str_replace(['(', ')'], '', $expression);
    $classes = str_replace(['"', '\''], '', $expression);
    $classes = str_replace(',', ' ', $classes);

    return '&lt;i class="fa ' . $classes . '" aria-hidden="false"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;';
});
</code></pre>

<p>Then it is as easy as it can get to use :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;label&gt; @icon('fa-user', 'fa-2x') User Name &lt;/label&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<p>You can also extend this idea for input, select etc. I think once you set such directives in a project, your blade views become readble. Plus less code in a bladel file is always better.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel tap vs tap vs pipe]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/08/laravel-tap-vs-tap-vs-pipe/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/08/laravel-tap-vs-tap-vs-pipe/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are wondering having tap 2 times in the article title is a mistake, apparently it is not. Laravel has large set of helper functions which are generic and helper functions specific to collections. Tap and pipe are very popular amongst laravel enthusiasts. Let's dive into each of of those to see what really makes them special and what differentiates them :</p>

<h3 id="the-tap-function-%3A">The tap() function :</h3>

<p>The reason of having tap 2 times in the article header is that, there are 2 implementations of tap helper function in laravel. One is in generic context and one specific to handling collections.</p>

<ul>
<li>The generic tap() function :</li>
</ul>

<p>The name tap suggests that it basically does set of actions using the value and then returns the value as if nothing happened. In other words, the tap function accepts two arguments <code>$value</code> and <code>a Closure</code>. The <code>$value</code> will be passed to the closure function. You can perform your actions in the closure where the return value of the Closure is irrelevant. At the end tap returns the same <code>$value</code> at the end.</p>

<p>For example :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user, function ($user) {

    $user-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail());

});
</code></pre>

<p>In the above snippet, we are passing <code>$user</code> instance to tap as first argument which is then cascaded as a parameter to closure. The closure will execute and basically send a new welcome email. Then control will come back to tap which will return the <code>$user</code> instance back.</p>

<p>Even you can just eliminate the closure and call function on it directly like below.</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user)-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail());
</code></pre>

<p>The above will still return the user instance. The beauty of it is, you can chain the tap calls. Let's say you need to update the user role, then send the welcome email and then assign user some permissions. You can chain it all like :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$user = tap($user)-&gt;update([
    'role' =&gt; 'Customer' 
])
-&gt;notify(new SendWelcomeEmail())
-&gt;assignPermissions('CustomerRole');
</code></pre>

<p>The use of this method can be handy when certain methods do not return the object as you want. A great example is the update method itself on the eloquent model. It returns integer when used otherwise. But if used as above with tap function, it returns the object it performed the update.</p>

<ul>
<li>The collection tap() function :</li>
</ul>

<p>The tap function for collection can be used in collection function chaining. I think of it similar to javascript debug breakpoints. You pin it to print something at a point of time in your javascript and then move ahead after removing the breakpoint.</p>

<p>For example consider following example :</p>

<pre><code class="php"><br />$customers = collect([
    ['name' =&gt; 'mihir',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'george', 'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'silver'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'nathen', 'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'platinum'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'steve',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'shawn',  'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'gold']
]);

$activeGoldCustomers = collect($customers)
    -&gt;where('is_active', true)
    -&gt;tap(function ($activeCustomers) {
        $this-&gt;sendActiveCustomerEmail($activeCustomers);
    })
    -&gt;where('category', 'gold')
    -&gt;tap(function ($goldCustomers) {
        $this-&gt;sendOfferCode('100%Discount');
    });
</code></pre>

<p>In above example, we are just returning the customers who are currently active and fall under category gold. However, using the tap function we can perform certain actions on the go as we filter those. When we filtered for <code>is_active = true</code>, we sent activation email. Then when we added another filter for <code>category = gold</code>, we sent offer code just for active customer from gold category.</p>

<p>You can also find this handy in dumping data for debugging during the developement cycle.</p>

<p>The fundamental concept of <code>tap()</code> is just use the value and perform actions but NEVER CHANGE the value. If you think then what can change the value? <code>pipe()</code> is the answer.</p>

<h3 id="the-pipe-function-%3A">The pipe() function :</h3>

<p>Pipe function is just applicable for collections. For example consider following example :</p>

<pre><code class="php"><br />$customers = collect([
    ['name' =&gt; 'mihir',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'george', 'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'silver'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'nathen', 'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'platinum'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'steve',  'is_active' =&gt; true,  'category' =&gt; 'gold'],
    ['name' =&gt; 'shawn',  'is_active' =&gt; false, 'category' =&gt; 'gold']
]);

$counts = collect($customers)
 -&gt;pipe(function($customers) {
    return [
        'active_count'      =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('is_active', true)-&gt;count(),
        'gold_count'        =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'gold')-&gt;count(),
        'silver_count'      =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'silver')-&gt;count(),
        'platinum_count'    =&gt; $customers-&gt;where('category', 'platinum')-&gt;count()
    ];
});
</code></pre>

<p>Above will basicaly return <code>[3, 3, 1, 1]</code>, but it is very clean and less code is always better.</p>

<p>Please note that the <code>pipe()</code> helper method is different than the <code>laravel pipelines</code>. However, if you read about pipelines, its is kind of similar conceptually to generic tap function where you can pass an object through multiple classes to perform set of task and then return the result value once all the tasks have been finished. A <a href="https://medium.com/@jeffochoa/understanding-laravel-pipelines-a7191f75c351">handy article</a> for the same is <a href="https://medium.com/@jeffochoa/understanding-laravel-pipelines-a7191f75c351">here</a> if you want a quick read.</p>

<p>Even if these methods are very handy, sometimes if you chain it to much it loses the element fo readability. I will suggest it is preferable to follow what the domain logic wants and group the similar processes together to tap or pipe.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel Module Pattern]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/06/laravel-module-pattern/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/06/laravel-module-pattern/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel has a folder structure which ties similar entities of MVC together e.g. controllers in one folder, views into another. There are few set-backs of this approach :</p>

<ul>
<li>If your project scales exponentially having lot of module, each of these directories scale as well. It becomes difficult to maintain.</li>
<li>If you want to remove the module entirely, there are files scattered in different folders to consider. This sometimes lead to unused files still present in your project repository.</li>
<li>Re-using a module into different project is a hassle (unless you have it installed coumpled as a plugin via composer)</li>
<li>While using code editors, as the module files are in different folders. We might need to expand the folders in project sidebar to view them at a glance. The scattered folder structure makes it difficult to for a quick view. (Forgive me for being picky here ;))</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="implementation-%3A">Implementation :</h4>

<p>Before you dive in to further sections, if you are familier with basic concepts of larave, most part of the code will be very familier to you. Tt is really easier that you might think.</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating the module :</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's create a new folder called <code>Modules</code> in the project root. (You might want to create it inside app folder, I prefer it this way.) To use the <code>\Modules</code> namespace, we need to autoload it from composer.json in the psr-4 section.</p>

<pre><code class="json"> "autoload": {
        "psr-4": {
            "App\\": "app/",
            "Modules\\": "Modules/",
        }
    },
</code></pre>

<p>Let's dump the updated autoloads by doing following from terminal shell :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">composer dump-autoload
</code></pre>

<p>Now we are good to start with the first module. Let's consider a ticket module where user can submit a ticket from frontend and we store it into the database. We will not focus much on the actual implementation of  the ticketing ystem. We will emphasize on the structure of module.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a new directory <code>Ticket</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a new directory <code>Ticket</code> inside <code>Modules</code> folder. I like to keep module names singular (Ticket instead of Tickets).</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating a service provider class :</li>
</ul>

<p>On a broader level, frameworks like laravel have special entry point wrappers which can find, register and instantiate the core functionalities. In case of Laravel it's the ServiceProvider class.</p>

<p>Create a new file <code>TicketServiceProvider.php</code> inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot() {}

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<p>To make sure laravel considers this while booting up, we need to register it. Add this inside <code>config/app.php</code>'s  <code>providers</code> array :</p>

<pre><code class="php">App\Modules\Ticket\TicketServiceProvider::class,
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Creating migrations :</li>
</ul>

<p>We need to create a table to store new ticket data. Create a folder <code>Migrations</code> inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>. 
Now we can create a new migration from terminal shell :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan make:migration create_tickets_table --path=Modules/Ticket/Migrations
</code></pre>

<p>It will create a new migration class inside <code>Modules/Ticket/Migrations</code> path. Let's add the table script :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

use Illuminate\Support\Facades\Schema;
use Illuminate\Database\Schema\Blueprint;
use Illuminate\Database\Migrations\Migration;

class CreateTicketsTable extends Migration
{
    /**
     * Run the migrations.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function up()
    {
        Schema::create('tickets', function (Blueprint $table) {
            $table-&gt;increments('id');
            $table-&gt;string('title')-&gt;nullable();
            $table-&gt;text('body')-&gt;nullable();
            $table-&gt;boolean('is_closed')-&gt;default(0);
            $table-&gt;timestamps();
        });
    }

    /**
     * Reverse the migrations.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function down()
    {
        Schema::dropIfExists('tickets');
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>However, you must have noticed that this is not coming from Laravel's default <code>database/migrations</code> folder. We need to inform laravel to load this file as well for running migration. It can be done from service provider by adding following in boot method.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot() {

        // Load ticket module migrations from 
        // `Modules/Ticket/Migrations` folder path
        $this-&gt;loadMigrationsFrom(__DIR__.'/Migrations');
    }

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now to run the migration from terminal shell :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan migrate
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Alternatively:</li>
</ul>

<p>If you are thinking <code>migrations are done very rarely, so why should we register it in service provider for a registration overhead?</code> Laravel has got you covered.</p>

<p>You can skip the step of doing <code>loadMigrationsFrom()</code> in service provider class. Instead you can specify the path while running migrations :</p>

<pre><code class="bash">php artisan migrate --path=Modules/Ticket/Migrations
</code></pre>

<p>If your project has CICD deployments, mostly it will just have the migrate command without the path option. The first method is preferable to keep it simple for deployments.</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating Model :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a file <code>Ticket.php</code> inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>. (You may create a <code>Models</code> folder inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code> and create model class inside it as per your preference.)</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Modules\Ticket;

use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Builder;
use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;

class Ticket extends Model
{
    /**
     * The table associated with the model.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $table = 'tickets';

    /**
     * The attributes that are mass assignable.
     *
     * @var array
     */
    protected $fillable = [
        'title',
        'body',
        'is_closed'
    ];

}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Creating Controller :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a new directory inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code> called <code>Http</code>. Let's create <code>TicketController.php</code> inside it :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket\Http;

use Illuminate\Http\Request;
use App\Http\Controllers\Controller;
use Modules\Ticket\Ticket;

class TicketController extends Controller
{
    /**
     * Display a form for the resource.
     *
     * @return \Illuminate\Http\Response
     */
    public function create()
    {
        return view('tickets.create');
    }

    /**
     * Store a newly created resource in storage.
     *
     * @param  Request  $request
     * @param  UserRepository $users
     * 
     * @return \Illuminate\Http\Response
     */
    public function store(Request $request)
    {
        $request-&gt;validate([
            'title' =&gt; 'string|required|max:255',
            'body'  =&gt; 'string|required'
        ]);

        // Create new ticket
        $ticket = Ticket::create($request-&gt;only('title', 'body'));

        return redirect()-&gt;route('ticket.new')-&gt;withSuccess('Thank you for raising a ticket. We will get back to you at the earliest.');
    }
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Creating Routes :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a new file called <code>TicketRoutes.php</code> inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php 

Route::group(['namespace' =&gt; 'Modules\Ticket', 'middleware' =&gt; ['web', 'auth']], function () {

    Route::get('ticket/new', [ 'as' =&gt; 'ticket.new', 'uses' =&gt; 'TicketController@create' ]);
    Route::post('ticket/store', [ 'as' =&gt; 'ticket.store', 'uses' =&gt; 'TicketController@store' ]);
});
</code></pre>

<p>We need to tell laravel to register these routes as those are coming from a custom folder. We can do that from service provider :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot() {

        // Load ticket module migrations from 
        // `Modules/Ticket/Migrations` folder path
        $this-&gt;loadMigrationsFrom(__DIR__.'/Migrations');

        // Load routes
        $this-&gt;loadRoutesFrom(__DIR__.'/TickerRoutes.php');
    }

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Creating Views :</li>
</ul>

<p>Create a new directory inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code> called <code>Views</code>. This will contain al views for our module. This is again not coming from Laravel's default <code>resources/views</code> folder. We need to tell laravel to load these views. It can be done from service provider by adding following in boot method.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot() {

        // Load ticket module migrations from 
        // `Modules/Ticket/Migrations`
        $this-&gt;loadMigrationsFrom(__DIR__.'/Migrations');

        // Load routes from `Modules/Ticket/TickerRoutes.php`
        $this-&gt;loadRoutesFrom(__DIR__.'/TickerRoutes.php');

        // Load views from `Modules/Ticket/Views`
        $this-&gt;loadViewsFrom(__DIR__.'/Views', 'ticket');
    }

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<p>Note : Sometimes you may see <code>loadViewsFrom()</code> called without the second argument which is the package name. The difference is if you want to render a view without a package name you do <code>ticket.create</code> (file path : <code>Modules/Ticket/Views/ticket/create.blade.php</code>. If you specify package name, you do <code>ticket::create</code> (file path : <code>Modules/Ticket/Views/create.blade.php</code>)</p>

<p>Let's create a simple view <code>create.blade.php</code> which basically has a form :</p>

<p></p>

<pre><code>@extends('layouts.app')

@section('content')
    &lt;div class="panel panel-default"&gt;
        &lt;div class="panel-body"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-md-4 col-md-offset-4"&gt;
                &lt;form role="form" method="POST" action="{{ route('ticket.store') }}"&gt;
                    @csrf
                    &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
                        &lt;label&gt;Title *&lt;/label&gt;
                        &lt;input class="form-control" placeholder="Title for your ticket" id="title" name="title"&gt;
                        @if ($errors-&gt;has('title'))
                            &lt;span class="invalid-feedback" role="alert"&gt;
                                &lt;strong&gt;{{ $errors-&gt;first('title') }}&lt;/strong&gt;
                            &lt;/span&gt;
                        @endif
                    &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
                        &lt;label&gt;Description *&lt;/label&gt;
                        &lt;textarea class="form-control" placeholder="How can we assist you?" id="body" name="body"&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
                        @if ($errors-&gt;has('body'))
                            &lt;span class="invalid-feedback" role="alert"&gt;
                                &lt;strong&gt;{{ $errors-&gt;first('body') }}&lt;/strong&gt;
                            &lt;/span&gt;
                        @endif
                    &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;button type="submit" class="btn btn-primary"&gt;Submit Ticket&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;/form&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
@endsection
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li>Creating Policies :</li>
</ul>

<p>If you would like to use policy to authorize the requests, create a file <code>TicketPolicy.php</code> inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Modules;

use App\User;


class TicketPolicy
{

    /**
     * Determines user access
     *
     * @param User $user
     * @return bool
     */
    public function index($user)
    {
        return true;
    }

    /**
     * Determines user access
     *
     * @param User $user
     * @return bool
     */
    public function store($user)
    {
        return true;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you must have thought by now, we need to register the policy using the laravel Gate contract inside service provider :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Modules\Ticket\Ticket.php;
use Modules\Ticket\TicketPolicy.php;
use Illuminate\Contracts\Auth\Access\Gate as GateContract;
use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot(GateContract $gate) {

        // Load ticket module migrations from 
        // `Modules/Ticket/Migrations`
        $this-&gt;loadMigrationsFrom(__DIR__.'/Migrations');

        // Load routes from `Modules/Ticket/TickerRoutes.php`
        $this-&gt;loadRoutesFrom(__DIR__.'/TickerRoutes.php');

        // Load views from `Modules/Ticket/Views`
        $this-&gt;loadViewsFrom(__DIR__.'/Views', 'ticket');

        // Load the policies from `Modules/Ticket/TicketPolicy.php`
        $gate-&gt;policy(Ticket::class, TicketPolicy::class);
    }

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li>Creating config files :</li>
</ul>

<p>We can have config files to access environmental variables specific for this module. For example in this ticket module let's say we need to configure an email to cc to. Create a file <code>TicketConfig.php</code> inside inside <code>Modules/Ticket</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

return [

    /*
    |--------------------------------------------------------------------------
    | Email to cc for submitted tickets
    |--------------------------------------------------------------------------
    |
    | Type : string
    |
    */

    'ticket_cc_email' =&gt; env('TICKET_CC_EMAIL', null),

];
</code></pre>

<p>Now, let's register this inside service provider.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Modules\Ticket;

use Modules\Ticket\Ticket.php;
use Modules\Ticket\TicketPolicy.php;
use Illuminate\Contracts\Auth\Access\Gate as GateContract;
use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider as BaseServiceProvider;

class TicketServiceProvider extends BaseServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Bootstrap any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function boot(GateContract $gate) {

        // Load ticket module migrations from 
        // `Modules/Ticket/Migrations`
        $this-&gt;loadMigrationsFrom(__DIR__.'/Migrations');

        // Load routes from `Modules/Ticket/TickerRoutes.php`
        $this-&gt;loadRoutesFrom(__DIR__.'/TickerRoutes.php');

        // Load views from `Modules/Ticket/Views`
        $this-&gt;loadViewsFrom(__DIR__.'/Views', 'ticket');

        // Load the policies from `Modules/Ticket/TicketPolicy.php`
        $gate-&gt;policy(Ticket::class, TicketPolicy::class);

        // Load the configurations from `Modules/Ticket/TicketConfig.php`
        $this-&gt;mergeConfigFrom(
            __DIR__.'/TicketConfig.php', 'ticket';
        );
    }

    /**
     * Register any application services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register() {}
}
</code></pre>

<p>We can then access the configurations as :</p>

<pre><code class="php">$ccEmail = config('ticket.ticket_cc_email');
</code></pre>

<p>Now you can see entire module is bundled to a single folder. Easy to manage. There is a downside of registrations inside service provider class which in general you do not worry about. However, this is structurally more intuitive and re-usable.</p>

<p>If you would like your module to have more extensive and detailed structure, you can simply use this ready composer plugin : <a href="https://nwidart.com/laravel-modules/v4/introduction">nwidart/laravel-modules</a></p>

<p>Note : The structure and coding style are my personal opinions. There can be multiple ways to accomplish the same result. I feel just knowing the possibility that it can be done, opens new doors of imaginations based on personal comfort.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laravel restricting unfiltered queries]]></title>
            <link href="https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/04/laravel-restricting-unfiltered-queries/"/>
            <updated>2019-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>https://techsemicolon.github.io/blog/2019/01/04/laravel-restricting-unfiltered-queries/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Laravel eloquent is a very powerful ORM. I came across a situation for a project of mine long time ago. There was a table <code>api_logs</code> which basically logged all API requests and responses. Evidently the table grew exponentially. One of the developers created an analytics module in which he forgot to add a where clause. It queried millions of rows at a time on production. It was a silly mistake but server was overwhelmed and you can imagine the rest of story (I can tell you it is not that good).</p>

<p>I imagined if there was a way to just throw an error if any function queries all rows from a table like <code>api_logs</code>. Two advantages :</p>

<ul>
<li>Error will be thrown during the development cycle where it's like an eye opener for the developer to make sure he adds filters.</li>
<li>If the develolper pushed the code to live by mistake, someone requesting the page will get the error page. I will be still having advantage with x% of customers getting an error rather than 100% of customer not using website when memory is exhausted. (If that query was in the header or footer on every page then basically it's over haha!)</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="implementation-%3A">Implementation :</h4>

<p>Short and simple, nothing fancy. We will just intercept an eloquent model for every query and check if it has a where clause. The best place for that is <code>boot</code> method of the model. I wish laravel has <code>retreiving</code> observer just like <code>created</code>, <code>updated</code> etc, which intercepts the query before it hits the database connection. (I am guessing as observers basically observes the state of a model instance, the state prior to <code>retreiving</code> is ideally an inception step of preparing collection of models/model and not yet a prime state to observe. And hence no such observer yet available.)</p>

<p>We can however use <code>\DB::listen()</code> listener as follows :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Model;

use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;

class ApiLog extends Model
{
    /**
     * The table associated with the model.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $table = 'api_logs';


    /**
     * The "booting" method of the model.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public static function boot(){

        parent::boot();

        \DB::listen(function($query) {
            //
        }); 
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Note that for Laravel version <code>5.1</code> and lower, the parameters of listen callback are <code>$sql, $bindings, $time</code> instead of just <code>$query</code>;</p>

<p>Now we have an listener, we need to get the query and check if it is selecting all rows. We will do it by regex on the raw sql.</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

    \DB::listen(function($query) {

        $table = (new self)-&gt;table;
        $pattern = "/from(\s)*?`?$table`?(\s)*$/m";

        if(preg_match($pattern, $query-&gt;sql)){
            throw new \Exception("Error : Running unfiltered queries on `$table` table is not allowed!");
        }
    }); 
}
</code></pre>

<p>Above preg match will catch all queries which do not have any clauses after the table syntax. Those can be select, update or delete queries.</p>

<p>Let's make this little more manageable by creating a trait and then using it in model. Create <code>RestrictsUnfilteredQueries.php</code> :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php 

namespace App\Model;

trait RestrictsUnfilteredQueries
{
    /**
     * Restrict unfiltered queries
     * 
     * @return void
     * @throws \Exception
     */
    public static function restrictUnfilteredQueries()
    {
        \DB::listen(function($query) {

            $table = (new self)-&gt;table;
            $pattern = "/from(\s)*?`?$table`?(\s)*$/m";

            if(preg_match($pattern, $query-&gt;sql)){
                throw new \Exception("Error : Running unfiltered queries on `$table` table is not allowed!");
            }
        }); 
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Using in the model's boot method :</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace App\Model;

use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;
use App\Model\RestrictsUnfilteredQueries;

class ApiLog extends Model
{
    use RestrictsUnfilteredQueries;

    /**
     * The table associated with the model.
     *
     * @var string
     */
    protected $table = 'api_logs';


    /**
     * The "booting" method of the model.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public static function boot(){

        parent::boot();

        self::restrictUnfilteredQueries(); 
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>And done! Now your server RAM will thank you forever for this ;)</p>

<p>Note that this will not work when you query using DB facade like <code>DB::select()</code> or <code>DB::table()-&gt;get()</code>.</p>

<p>You may alternatively cater this as well by having <code>DB::listen()</code> inside a service provider's boot method. It will listen to all sort of queries. However, it might be too much to listen all queries.</p>

<p>There might be better way of implementing the same, I did it this way considering the urgency of situation. It is still there in project since then and working perfectly.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>